Finding Aid for Palmer Christian papers, 1841-1953
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Palmer Christian papers 1841-1953
Christian, Palmer.
1.3 linear foot
85998 Aa 2
Organist and professor of music at the University of Michigan, and other members of the Christian family; correspondence, clippings, concert programs, and other papers re his teaching, concert career, European student days, etc.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Palmer Christian (donor no. 3620 ) and came to the library in 1960.
The collection is open to research.
Palmer Christian was born May 3, 1885 in Kankakee, Ill. He studied at the Cosmopolitan School of Music in Chicago, then in 1909 attended the Royal Conservatory of Music at Leipzig, studying organ with Karl Straube and theory with Gustav Shreck. He also studied organ with Alexandre Guilmant and voice with Alfred Behrens in Paris. Returning to the United States, Christian was municipal organist at Denver for two years, then went to Chicago where he was professor of sacred music at the McCormick Theological Institute and organist of the Fourth Presbyterian Church until 1923. In 1924, he came to the University of Michigan as professor of organ and as the University organist. As an organist, Christian also made several trans-continental tours through Europe and also played with leading orchestras in the United States. He died February 19, 1947.
The Palmer Christian collection is comprised of four series: Correspondence and other papers; Programs and reviews of recitals; Madrigals; and Photographs. The correspondence is noteworthy for long-term correspondents such as symphony conductor Eric De Lamarter who regularly communicated with Christian for over twenty year period beginning in 1925 and from Eugene Ormandy. During World War II, Christian received many letters from former students then serving in the military.
Subjects:
Christian, Palmer.; Europe--Description and travel.; Hill Auditorium (University of Michigan); Palmer, Alonzo Benjamin, 1815-1887.; Spain--History--Civil War, 1936-1939.; Travelers.; United States. Army. Illinois Infantry Regiment, 76th (1862-1865). Company E.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; University of Michigan. School of Music.; Voyages and travels.; World War, 1939-1945.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Christian, Palmer.; Christian family.; Europe.; Hill Auditorium (University of Michigan); Musicians.; Organs.; Palmer family.; Tourism--Europe.
Contributors:
Barbour, Edwin Scott.; Burton, Marion Le Roy, 1874-1925.; De Lamarter, Eric, 1880-1953.; Eastburn, Isaac M.; Homs, Pablo.; Johnson, Thor.; Ormandy, Eugene, 1899-1985.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence and other papers
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1841-1908 (Box 1)
    (includes Civil War letters of Isaac M. Eastburn, Co. E, 76th Illinois Regiment; includes also copy of will of Alonzo B. Palmer)
  - 1909 (Box 1)
    (include letters written while a student in Leipzig and Paris; these letters from abroad continue through 1911)
  - January-June 1910 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1910 (Box 1)
  - 1911 (Box 1)
  - 1918-1925 (Box 1)
    (includes letter, 1923, from Marion LeRoy Burton re. appointment as president of the University of Michigan; also correspondence, February 18, 1925, with Eric De Lamarter)
  - 1928-1934 (Box 1)
    (include letters from Edwin Scott Barbour, March 30, April 11, 1928, re. organist job at Grosse Pointe Memorial Church)
  - 1935-1936 (Box 1)
    (includes material about Hill Auditorium organ, 1936; letters from Pablo Homs, 1936, perhaps a fascist supporter, during the Spanish Civil War; also includes correspondence with Eric De Lamarter)
  - 1937 (Box 1)
  - 1938 (Box 1)
  - 1939-1941 (Box 1)
    (includes letter analyzing career of Thor Johnson, July 21, 1939)
  - 1942-1943 (Box 1)
  - 1944-1945 (Box 1)
    (includes letter, December 15, 1944, containing history of organ department of University of Michigan Music School; and letters from Eugene Ormandy, January 8, January 25, 1944, concerning concerts at Hill Auditorium)
  - 1946 (Box 1)
    (includes material about Hill Auditorium organ)
  - January 1-February 20, 1947 (Box 1)
  - February 21-22, 1947 (Box 1)
  - February 23-24, 1947 (Box 1)
    (includes letter from Thor Johnson)
  - February 25-28, 1947 (Box 1)
  - March 1947 (Box 1)
  - April-May 1947 (Box 1)
  - 1948-1953 (Box 1)
- Programs and reviews of recitals
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1896-1913 (Box 1)
  - 1914 (Box 1)
  - 1915-1919 (Box 1)
  - 1920-1922 (Box 1)
  - 1923 (Box 1)
  - 1924 (Box 1)
  - January-March 1925 (Box 1)
  - April-December 1925 (Box 1)
  - 1926 (Box 1)
  - 1927 (Box 1)
  - 1928 (Box 1)
  - 1929 (Box 1)
  - 1930 (Box 1)
  - 1931 (Box 1)
  - 1932 (Box 1)
  - 1933 (Box 1)
  - 1934 (Box 1)
  - 1935-1939 (Box 1)
  - 1940-1941 (Box 1)
  - 1942-1946 (Box 1)
  - 1947-1950 (Box 1)
- Compositions
  - Madrigals (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Portraits as child (Box 2)
  - Portraits, formal and informal (Box 2)
  - Portraits at organ (Box 2)
  - Palmer and Lois Christian (Box 2)
  - Christian and Palmer families (Box 2)
  - Groups (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Album (Box 2)